Guide to the Hoyt Family Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Hoyt Family Papers
1855-1924
Hoyt family.
2.5 linear feet (5 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0623
4078915
A collection of the personal papers, including personal correspondence and financial documents, of the family of James Otis Hoyt (1842-1896), a prominent New York Lawyer.
Biographical Note
James Otis Hoyt (1842-1896) was born in Haverhill, Massachusetts. He attended Phillips Exeter Academy and Harvard University, from which he graduated in 1865. Upon graduation, he spent a year as a teacher at Saint Mark's School in Southborough, Massachusetts. He returned to Harvard to pursue a degree in Law, which he received in 1868; while there, he was a proctor and teacher of history. He then moved to New York, where he worked briefly in several law firms before founding his own firm with Richard Christian (R.C.) Fellows in 1871. The firm would later become Fellows, Hoyt, and Schell (with Edward H. Schell), and finally Hoyt and Schell. Hoyt was a director and general counsel to the Manhattan Life Insurance Company, and general counsel to the National Butchers' and Drovers' bank and the Manhattan Savings Bank. In 1876 he married Fellows's sister, Emily Fellows (1847-1909), and the two had three daughters: Mary (1877-19??), Harriet (1880-19??), and Emily (1883-1919). Hoyt died unexpectedly of an illness in 1896. Mary attended Bryn Mawr from 1895-1898. From 1916-1917 she studied nursing and wireless signal work and from 1917-1919 she worked as an Auxiliary Nurse for the American Red Cross in France.
Scope and Content
The Hoyt Family collection is comprised primarily of the papers of James Otis Hoyt, his wife, Emily (née Fellows), and two of their three daughters, Emily and Mary Fellows Hoyt. These papers include personal correspondence, financial documents, and printed materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series:
Series I: James Otis Hoyt, 1855-1896
Series II: Mrs. James Otis Hoyt (Emily Fellows), 1885-1909
Series III: Other Family Members, 1882-1924
Series IV: Documents, 1860s-1910s
Subjects
Fellows family.; Hoyt family.; Schell, Augustus, 1812-1884.; American Red Cross.; Harvard College.; Harvard Law School.; Harvard University.; St. Mark's School.; Woodlawn Cemetery (New York, N.Y.); Lawyers.; World war, 1914-1918--War work--Red Cross.; Correspondence.; Invoices.; Love letters.; Picture postcards.; Visiting cards.
Gift of Joseph Katz, 1965
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
- Series I: Hoyt, James Otis, 1855-1896
  The bulk of James Otis Hoyt's papers date from the 1860s, when he was a student at Harvard College and Harvard Law School. Of his correspondence, most are letters of a personal nature, including a number of love letters from a woman named Sara W. There are also a number of his writings, including a dissertation written in his junior year at Harvard entitled "On Carey's View of Trade as the Instrument of Commerce" and a later work entitled "Concerning the Liability of Partners as to Third Partners." There are also financial documents (mostly bills), and teaching materials from his time as a teacher at St. Mark's School and at Harvard.
  - General, 1860s-1890s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exeter and Harvard, 1860s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial, 1860s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Sara, 1864-1864 April (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Sara, 1864 May-1867 undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Teaching Materials, circa 1860s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings
    - Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Carey's View of Trade as the Instrument of Commerce," 1865 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Concerning the Liability of Partners as to Third Persons," undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - School Compositions, 1850s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - 1861-1863 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1864 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1865 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1866 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1867 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1868-1896 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Circa 1860s, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 7 to 8)
- Series II: Hoyt, Mrs. James Otis (Emily Fellows), 1885-1909
  Mrs. Hoyt's papers are composed of personal correspondence and financial documents. Personal correspondence includes letters from friends (many are condolences written at the time of her husband's death) and from Mary, written during her time at Bryn Mawr. Among the financial documents are insurance policies, a deed to a family plot in Woodlawn Cemetery, and correspondence and official papers relating to the estates of her brother, Richard Christian Fellows, and Augustus Schell.
  - Estates of Richard Christian Fellows and Augustus Schell, 1897-1905 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Estate, 1911-1918 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Financial Documents, 1896-1908 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - 1885-1898 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1900-1909 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III: Other Family Members, 1882-1924
  This series contains the papers of Emily Hoyt (sometimes called Pansy), Mary Fellows Hoyt, and James O. Hoyt's mother, Mrs. James B. Hoyt. Emily's papers include financial documents and personal correspondence, the bulk of which are letters written to her by Mary in 1917 and 1918 during her time as an American Red Cross nurse in France. Mary's papers include her personal correspondence and financial documents. There are also several official papers for both sisters, including an automobile registration and Mary's passport. The letters addressed to Mrs. James B. Hoyt are mostly from her young grandchildren. The folder titled "Unidentified Correspondence" includes letters addressed to "Miss Hoyt" and to "The Misses Hoyt."
  - Hoyt, Mary and Emily--Official Documents, 1890-1923 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Hoyt, Emily
    - Financial Documents, 1914-1919 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Emily--Letters from Mary Hoyt, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Mary Hoyt, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Hoyt, Mary F.
    - Financial Documents, 1909-1919 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Personal Correspondence
      - 1885-1905 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - 1906 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - 1907-1824 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Hoyt, Mrs. James B.--Personal Correspondence, 1882-1891 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified Correspondence 1905-1921 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Documents, 1860s- 1910s
  This series is comprised of the less personal documents that were included in the family's collection. There are a number of calling cards and invitations, and ephemera, such as advertisements, programs, and mailings from various clubs. Of particular interest is a large collection of American and European postcards from the 1900s and 1910s, amassed by Mary Fellows Hoyt. Also included are the plans for a boat, a house, and a building which is most likely the family's townhouse at 310 west 75th st. in New York, built in 1893.
  - Blueprints, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Financial Documents, 1910s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Picture Postcards, 1903-1919 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Picture Postcards, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Printed Material, 1860s (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material, 1910s (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Writings and Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Visiting Cards and Invitations, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)